Endless landscapes,
crossed by Indians dressed in their ponchos,
this postcard image,
This is Bolivia.
This country,
the poorest in Latin America,
As large as twice the size of France,
is populated by 9 million inhabitants.
More than 2 million of them live in La Paz,
the capital,
and its suburb El Alto,
the great popular city of Indians and sailors.
These two cities lie at the foot of the sacred mountains of the Altiplano,
a vast and high plateau that stretches along the Royal Cordillera of the Andes and extends into its neighbors in Chile,
from Argentina and Peru.
My name is Gerarda Morales.
I am Indian and Mara.
like a quarter of my Bolivian brothers.
I am descended from a civilization that is over 3000 years old.
of the first great Andean empire,
that of Tihuanacu,
founded on the shores of Lake Titicaca.
Our ancestors had extensive knowledge of agronomy.
in architecture,
in medicine and astronomy.
We are a proud people.
We love our languages.
our traditions,
our gods,
our way of life on these otherwise hostile high plateaus.
I live in the city,
in El Alto.
Here,
We are almost at an altitude of 4000 meters.
I see these majestic mountains every day.
The very highest peaks are covered with glaciers.
Ilimani,
the Iliampu,
the Wainapotosi,
the Tchakaltaya.
In our country,
These are gods worshipped throughout the country.
Bolivia is experiencing a paradox.
With global warming,
Glaciers provide a lot of water.
But the melting accelerated so much that it could not be anticipated.
So this excess water is lost.
In the Altiplano,
We do not benefit from the water from glaciers.
intended for the city.
Climate change is resulting in a continuous decrease in rainfall, leading to a growing rural exodus towards El Alto.
This demographic shift exacerbates the city's water access problems.
primarily due to poverty and the outdated state of the network.
In El Alto,
I have a small house,
almost at the edge of town,
in the Inti neighborhood,
which means the sunny district.
I run a small recycling business there.
That's partly how I earn a living.
I collect plastics,
metals,
everything that can be recycled,
and I resell them to a processing company.
This reduces waste and there is less of it along the roads.
I also teach from time to time.
I learned traditional crafts from my mother and then I continued to make them myself.
All of this provides a living for my father and me.
I am also the president of a producers' association,
farmers and artisans of the Altiplano.
ICAB,
which means integration of the emara communities of Bolivia.
I regularly travel the roads of the Altiplano to meet my brothers and sisters from the association.
More than 50 families spread across 24 rural communities.
I haven't always lived in El Alto.
I arrived here 25 years ago.
Before,
I used to live in a small village not far from here,
at Colque Alta,
with my family.
I was a shepherdess.
And it was my brother, a schoolteacher, who wanted me to go and study in the city to ensure a better life for myself.
That's what happened to me.
but this is not the case for all migrants in El Alto.
When I arrived in this new neighborhood,
There was no running water.
I had to go get the water from Valentina's,
my neighbor,
which had a private well.
NOW,
I have a tap in my home and it has changed my life.
But not everyone is in the same boat.
Some neighborhoods do not have running water.
El Alto is a long, narrow city.
It stretches for several kilometers.
Less than a century ago,
It was just a suburb of La Paz,
the capital.
Today,
this popular city,
predominantly Emara
it alone has almost a million inhabitants.
Each day,
New migrants from the Altiplano are settling there.
The city's population growth reaches 5%
per year.
Water is a problem in El Alto.
This one comes from glaciers.
And it is difficult for the poorest populations to access.
Most residents cannot afford the $150 for individual connection and consumption charges.
knowing that the average salary is $100.
Neighborhoods without mains water connections have communal fountains or wells.
The town hall connected us to drinking water because the whole neighborhood mobilized for months.
I know that the water we use comes from glaciers,
that global warming is responsible for their melting.
And I'm worried about it.
As president of ICAB,
I requested an interview with the mayor.
We would like to know about his program for private access to drinking water for the residents of Alalto.
Mr. Mayor,
I would like to ask you a few questions about the number of inhabitants and the distribution of water according to the districts.
El Alto has approximately one million inhabitants.
Currently,
Water reserves are insufficient for the entire population.
This means almost 250,000 people are not supplied with drinking water.
Because its distribution is not yet guaranteed for everyone.
The unplanned population growth of our city is the cause of this poor water management.
A significant number of migrants are arriving,
settle in,
build their habitat.
Their primary need is water.
What I mean is,
It's not that we're refusing to supply these people with water,
these 250,000 people.
But the problem is that we have not yet succeeded in connecting them to the main water distribution networks.
Often,
new housing developments do not have water for the first two months after they are built.
One of our major concerns is that they have one or two public fountains available in the meantime.
And one of the first concerns is the extension of a gallery so that there is at least...
one or two common pilettes.
Go ahead,
You're going to leave.
Mr. Mayor,
We visited the Santa Cruz maritime district.
And we found that people were using wells or the few public fountains because they didn't have access to water at home.
A large number of them have applied to the town hall for water.
but nothing came of it.
They had to fend for themselves.
This place is important for the community.
This is the only public water source in this area.
We would like to have a water supply in every house.
But there are so many steps to take and it's so expensive.
And as you know,
The government doesn't have the resources.
We are responsible for covering all installation costs.
Where does the water come from?
We brought it from the Santo Domingo neighborhood.
And in order to achieve this,
Everyone had to participate.
All the neighbors?
Of course,
We all worked the land with our own tools.
Everyone also provided financial support.
Each neighbor was assigned a work site of approximately 4 tons.
We dug a trench 4 meters wide,
Then we took care of the piping,
and finally we had to buy more accessories.
The box that protects the tap was made by us.
All participants were given a key to open the padlock.
Of course,
Those who did not provide financial assistance are not entitled to the key.
Mr. Mayor,
if we don't address the melting of the glaciers,
We will run out of water more and more.
year after year.
What solution is being offered to him?
I am not an expert when it comes to water and its distribution in El Alto.
But specialists will be able to find solutions to these future problems.
What I know,
The problem is getting worse.
Technicians are predicting a very significant decrease in water due to the melting of our glaciers within the next 5 years.
As it currently constitutes the most important source of water supply,
This is therefore very worrying.
Moreover,
We also have technical problems with the drinking water network.
In anticipation of all this,
Citizens must learn to be careful and to conserve this vital resource.
And we must let the specialists do their work so that they can find the right solutions.
The waste of tap water has reached considerable proportions in El Alto.
up to 40%
of water loss.
Water seeping into the ground,
The network is leaking due to the age of the pipes,
not to mention the population that connects illegally.
The solutions are obvious.
To restore the water distribution network to working order and to build dams in the mountains to regulate the water from the glaciers.
Simple,
but exorbitant for a city that lives below the poverty line.
And it's urgent.
because in 2050,
The region's population will have doubled.
The Jackal Taïa is living its last ice age.
Just a few years ago,
This small glacier was the highest ski area in the world.
The average annual rainfall deficit in the Chacal Taïa area increased from 60 cm of water between 1963 and 1983 to more than 1.20 m between 1983 and 2003.
thus accelerating the melting of the glacier.
80%
Glaciers in the Andes are similar in size to the Taia jackal.
and will have disappeared before the end of the century.
The mountain gods in our region are called the achachilas.
Honoring the deities is important in our traditions.
I asked José,
a Yatiri sorcerer whom I know well,
to come and make offerings on the Chacaltaya to protect its last snows.
In Aymara,
Chacaltaya means icy road.
I,
I saw him disappear.
We live in harmony with the land and sea.
Pachamama.
Goddess among goddesses,
which brings abundance to those who worship it.
Our ancestors always respected the divine signs observed in the sky and in nature.
to know when to sow,
when to harvest.
José invokes Pachamama and the Achachilas.
the mountain gods.
He asks them for mercy.
He wants to calm their anger.
The fire must burn well.
Otherwise, it's a bad omen.
The sign that we have not prayed sincerely.
Located less than 100 km from El Alto,
The glaciers of the Cordillera Real provide most of the region's water consumption.
The melting of glaciers has accelerated over the last ten years.
In 1980,
Scientists have calculated that Huayna Potosi,
a glacier in the Zongo Valley,
had receded by 30 meters in 200 years.
Since that date,
In less than 30 years,
He lost again
50 meters.
This is the conclusion reached by glaciologists from the IRD.
the Research Institute for Development,
which monitors the evolution of glaciers in the Andes, and particularly those in Bolivia.
If we invoke the gods with enough faith,
Then our wishes can come true.
But I want to understand the misfortune that is striking our mountains.
and to know everything that is within the power of men to fight against the agony of our glaciers.
I wanted to accompany Edson and Patrick,
two glaciologists,
up to the Zongo glacier.
Is this your first time going up onto a glacier?
Yes,
This is the first time.
You'll see,
You won't regret it.
It's magnificent.
Yes,
I am always dazzled by the spectacle and what's more, the weather is beautiful today.
Let's enjoy this splendor and sit down for a moment if you don't mind.
We are still at 5500 meters,
very close to the Zongo glacier,
which is part of Huayna Potosi,
the highest peak in Bolivia.
We have been studying this glacier since
1991. There are small glaciers like Chacal Taya which are lower mountains.
below
5000 meters.
This category of glaciers is destined to disappear.
Only the highest glaciers,
like the Zongo,
El Huayna Potosi or Ilimani,
will resist and not disappear completely.
but will nevertheless suffer a significant setback.
Once a month,
We are coming up here to measure the mass loss of the glacier.
Over the last 30 years,
The glaciers have retreated by 50 meters and that's far too much.
The glacier is almost losing
50 meters high.
Oh yes ?
Yes,
That's a lot.
And what is the cause?
One of the main causes,
It's climate change.
But other factors come into play.
With global warming,
The melting is accelerating significantly.
Look at,
all the peaks you see over there in the distance,
just a few years ago,
They were snow-covered and now...
And now,
There's nothing left.
Effectively.
The successive layers of ice have all disappeared.
And there are also the fumes emitted by the factories,
gases.
That must be a factor.
No ?
Yes,
Without a doubt.
This is a very serious problem because it's not just Bolivia that is affected.
but the entire planet.
Most of the energy we use,
especially in developed countries,
fuels,
gases,
are harmful to the climate.
Are there solutions to these problems?
What are the solutions to prevent this?
It's hard to say.
Otherwise,
to consider obvious measures that would allow the planet to breathe and thus slow down climate change.
This regression is not limited to Bolivia,
but the entire Andes mountain range,
and also the mountains of Europe,
The Himalayas too.
It's a global effect.
NOW,
We need to see how we adapt to this change and how people could consider common solutions.
Obviously,
These solutions should be considered at a local level.
But this is a problem we need to solve for all countries in the world.
I am amazed.
I never imagined I would one day be so close to heaven.
I'm worried too.
Edson and Patrick told me that we currently have more water than usual.
but that a day will come when we will desperately lack it.
How will our brothers and sisters and Mara manage to survive in this already very dry region?
It rains very little here.
And I'm afraid they'll abandon their land because of it.
Water from melting glaciers is abundant,
but its management,
Its distribution and the resources deployed are lacking.
It was at the foot of the Tony Condoriri glacier that one of the two dams that supplies El Alto was built.
It can collect up to 24 billion liters of water.
In order to compensate for the retreat of glaciers and to meet the demand for water,
Scientists agreed that new water reservoirs would be needed.
in the next five years.
But despite the urgency,
Financial resources are lacking.
The water from the glacier we visited is held back in this dam.
We are taking advantage of the rain and the melting glacier.
This water is stored and thus,
during the dry season,
We will not lack water.
Of course.
Ah,
This is to avoid waste.
Isn't that right?
That's obvious.
So all of this comes from the glacier?
Yes.
The dam fills with rainwater and what comes from the melting glacier.
The glacier,
You see,
functions like a dam.
It retains the water in a snowy state and releases it little by little.
They both function in a similar way.
Could we also build dams elsewhere?
Of course,
That's desirable.
And without a doubt,
in the future,
We will build several of them.
in order to have water reserves in various places.
But it is very difficult to find a suitable location for construction sites of this size.
There are specialists,
like hydroelectric engineers,
who are thinking about this.
And for cities as densely populated as Alto,
That would be very desirable.
Perfectly.
And the Alto,
as you know,
is developing at a rapid pace.
For now,
We have some problems with the water.
and in the years to come,
They will intensify.
Given climate change,
The glaciers are receding,
are shrinking.
It is likely that in the coming years,
We will have more water following the thaw.
But this source will run out.
then we will have to use rainwater.
Although here too,
There may be changes,
It's possible that it will rain even less.
And if the temperature rises even more,
Some of the water retained here will evaporate.
All of this will have serious consequences for us.
Build another dam,
It's essential.
But this will primarily benefit the city.
Most people living in the vast countryside of the Altiplano do not have access to water.
What will become of them?
Oh,
Ciao!
Bye,
Bye!
Hi,
Wow!
In order to better control water and its distribution in the Altiplano,
We are building reservoirs.
Most of them are supplied by water from dams and located halfway between the glacier and the villages.
Kilometers of trenches are dug,
Kilometers of pipes are laid to bring water to the communities.
Only these tanks,
smaller and significantly easier to build than dams,
are still very rare in this desert region.
Life is difficult in the altiplano.
It's arid,
it's cold,
Few plants grow at this altitude.
This is often not enough to support families who migrate to the city.
thinking they would earn more money.
Our cultures,
Our traditions are declining with this exodus.
I try, in my own small way, to keep the people I know in their village.
Along with my other brothers and sisters who are members of the association,
We are trying to develop the income of our communities in the Altiplano.
We support them in their crafts which we collect and sell in fair trade shops in cities and in markets.
We are also encouraging them to develop their agriculture.
their craftsmanship,
to educate the youngest children.
I place a lot of emphasis on education.
Each community receives my visit approximately once a month.
Today,
I'm going to Viliake.
a rather poor village,
which has very little water and does not yet have reservoirs.
I plan to ask Doniato,
one of the community leaders,
if he has thought of any solutions.
and what can be done.
At Vilake,
We have chosen the cooperative agricultural system.
For the moment,
it is our village that is responsible for sowing the oats.
In 4 or 5 years,
The plan is to grow potatoes.
But this culture is unpredictable.
We need water.
If we normally have rain,
We harvest more or less enough for our subsistence.
And if rain is scarce,
We are experiencing a shortage.
Look at,
This oat crop did not grow as it should have due to the lack of rain.
But last month,
There was a big storm and the little fodder we had was damaged.
As a result,
It is our animals who suffer.
SO...
So there's no chance of seeing this oat grow any further?
If,
with God's help,
we would like to implement irrigation,
But it's not obvious.
The terrain being uneven,
This requires a lot of investment and at the moment we are blocked by a lack of resources.
The best solution would be to bring water from the mountain via the Huayna Potosi glacier.
who is up there.
To solve this crucial irrigation problem,
We would need to build a reservoir.
No ?
Quite.
At the top of this hill,
We could store water there.
And what's more,
It would blend in well with the landscape.
It will be magnificent.
We would use the rock to block the water.
And by the grace of God,
We would have a large water source that would supply the village,
the inhabitants,
animals,
the crops.
With its rugged terrain and hills covered in hard rock,
That would be a difficult and formidable challenge.
because it would be made by human hands.
And is it urgent?
The sooner the better.
Can you describe the village to me?
Villaque is made up of 6 zones,
6 cantons if you prefer.
And does everyone have the same need for water?
Unfortunately,
The repercussions on the population are being felt more and more each day.
Currently,
There are still 700 families,
But for how long?
We see it every day.
Leaving for El Alto, the village is becoming depopulated, the hemorrhage must be stopped, so you can understand the urgent need for work and that it is crucial for those who remain.
This particularly affects young people, who are the most impacted, and some who migrate to the city in search of work because here, once the planting season is over, the countryside is deserted.
There's nothing to be done here, the ground is too dry
SO,
with good investments,
It would be possible for us to cultivate everything that can be found in the region.
We could even expand the arable areas with the virgin land that is up there.
What is the land area surrounding the village?
Just around Villake,
We have 15,300 hectares.
Do you realize if all of this has been cultivated?
Yes,
That's a lot of land.
but to work with them,
We would need to bring back those who have left.
Another great challenge.
With easier access to water,
Many villages in the Altiplano could grow any vegetables they wanted.
to provide for their needs,
to become self-sufficient and thus put a stop to rural exodus,
which is a source of suffering for the Emara people, who are so attached to their land and traditions.
The old sorcerer Pedro invokes Pachamama for good rains during the next harvest.
He also asks her to help the community with the construction of a reservoir.
Today I am happy.
I will be attending the launch of the construction of a drinking water reservoir in Palcoco.
a village on the Plateau.
I will be able to find out more and pass the solution on to Doniato and the other ICAB communities.
All beneficiaries of the reservoir,
those from Palcoco, but also from neighboring villages
are gathering today to begin the community project.
Whenever major works are undertaken,
We ask for protection from Pachamama.
It's a tradition in our family.
and a real party.
To achieve their goal,
The villagers and municipal authorities must show patience and determination.
Often,
Several years of negotiations are needed to convince the communities.
Obtain the necessary administrative authorizations and finally begin the work.
All that's needed is to capture the springs flowing down from the glacier.
Once the process is initiated,
A few weeks are enough to dig kilometers of trenches that connect the reservoir and the homes.
The vital existence of nature is one of the first things that allows us to do.
The total number of these reservoirs is firmly in the minds of the families who will benefit from this providential water.
My dearest brothers,
my dearest sisters,
gentlemen specialists.
Today we are here to keep you informed about the Colonna project,
which must start right now.
We are going to begin work on the drinking water reservoir.
planned within the framework of this project,
while respecting our traditions.
Among us are the leaders of Viluyo,
Machacamarca,
Palcoco,
Condoriri,
Coastline,
Villa Andino.
We are all committed to successfully completing this project.
The division of tasks will be explained to you before the start of the work.
Let us not forget to respect our rituals of offerings to the earth and sea.
Pachamama,
to the forces of the mountain.
Thank you for listening to me.
dear brothers,
Dear sisters.
Dear brothers,
Dear sisters,
We will now give the floor to Gerarda.
which represents the Association of Producers and Artisans of Bolivia.
It's your turn.
Gerarda.
THANKS,
dear brothers,
Dear sisters.
Hello to the representatives of the Palcoco town hall,
to the eight representatives of the communities.
"I am very happy to be among you this morning and delighted that this project is finally coming to fruition.
This is a great day for everyone here.
“Last Saturday,
I went up onto the glacier with glaciologists and they explained to me the evolution of the climate and water in relation to global warming.
I am pleased to know that you are going to build a water reservoir and that you will be able to lay the first stone today.
The glaciologists told me that in a few years we are going to run out of water.
We must therefore be careful.
I was able to witness the phenomenon with my own eyes.
This water reservoir is essential and many more will need to be built in the coming years.
At the beginning of this project, which dates back to 2003,
We were only two communities.
Then all the other communities joined us.
They understood that living with other communities,
with the same comfort as in the city,
was a good motivation.
And then we started talking about the melting glaciers,
And that was decisive.
The sole purpose of this work is access to drinking water.
essential for everyone's survival.
All of this has taken on considerable proportions.
I remain convinced that,
with God's help,
and thanks to our faith,
We will succeed.
Today, with this inaugural first stone, we are reaching the point where the irrigation system can be extended.
Will all communities benefit from this project?
This is for the seven communities,
My brother.
And from there onward,
It will be useful.
All communities,
obviously.
The architect who designed the drinking water reservoir made sure that everyone could benefit from this water.
I am very confident.
Our goal will be achieved through the solidarity of each and every one of us.
Despite this natural spirit of solidarity among the Indians and Maras of the Altiplano,
Reservoir projects are still too rare.
due to a lack of initiative and especially because of often precarious technical and financial resources.
The majority of the fragmented land belongs to communities that must pay for access to water.
Some private landowners have made an effort to ensure that the fragmented land can be reused.
have the means to have private access
which allows them to practice irrigation on the altiplano for extensive crops.
They also develop specific techniques,
such as drip irrigation,
which requires very little water while ensuring good yields.
Faced with global warming and water scarcity,
It's a method that allows you to use less water and use it better.
This drip irrigation technique pays for itself in one year.
With two harvests per year,
It allows...
to a farmer to live better than an employee in the city of El Alto.
I'm going to Calamarca.
I am going to meet Walter Fernandez.
a farmer,
who will show me this drip irrigation technique.
I am curious to see with my own eyes what he manages to do in the altiplano.
As you have seen,
Everything is dry.
It is winter and almost the entire harvest has been completed.
as you can see.
And when was the irrigation stopped?
It's been two weeks.
Normally,
We should have stopped more than a month ago.
Is that why it's drying out like that?
Yes,
but thanks to this method,
We had a very good first harvest.
But irrigating the fields only affects part of our production.
Here,
the drip method is used.
in the greenhouses at the back.
Besides,
all our remaining harvests are there.
Right now,
We produce potatoes there.
Potatoes.
And what else?
Beans,
onions,
sometimes carrots
peas,
salads,
but also barley.
to feed the livestock.
How many harvests do you have in a year?
We start sowing in August and we harvest twice a year.
And all of this is possible thanks to irrigation?
Yes,
Water is needed constantly and the land must be worked continuously.
Is it useful to other communities?
No,
We are a private organization.
We are not associated with the other farmers.
And where does your irrigation water come from?
We pay for our access to the community drinking water source.
But since this water must be distributed equally among everyone,
We also invested in a personal water pump that draws its water from a lower source.
This water is used for the fields.
whereas for the greenhouse,
we only use the one from the community.
Of course,
If there is a restriction or if we have an additional need,
We cannot take drinking water from the community.
So in that case,
Are you using your water pump?
Yes.
Otherwise,
we risk a confrontation with the community.
And that would be a problem for us.
And is there always water in the surrounding area?
Yes,
here,
There is water,
but it is very poorly distributed.
That's the only problem.
SO,
we should only use it for domestic purposes.
We must never forget that in other places,
There is no water at all.
I've never seen so many vegetables in my life.
That's incredible.
Each backblow produced.
That amazed me.
I can't wait to tell my brothers and sisters all about this.
Having such greenhouses would change their lives and would stop the depopulation of villages once and for all.
Whether it's dams,
reservoirs or drip irrigation,
Solutions exist for future water shortages.
Only,
They must be put in place very quickly and on a large scale to retain this water that is rushing down the mountains.
But how do we do it?
when you are one of the poorest countries on the planet,
endowed with a GDP of only $2.60 per capita,
and that we are suffering the climatic consequences of a development from which we have never benefited.
Waiting for,
Glaciers are melting and 2 million people depend on them today.
I don't know what will happen in 10 or 20 years.
Will our communities in the Altiplano have enough greenhouses?
of tanks?
to stay up there,
As close as possible to the gods in Tchatchilas?
We all have a part of the answer.
For my part,
I will continue my travels across the Altiplano,
to support my brothers and sisters and my rat,
so that our traditions may live on.
our culture and our small villages.
But in the future,
I'm going to tell them what I saw.
It is possible to fight against the lack of water.
It is our turn to watch over Pachamama,
land-sea,
so that once again,
She watches over us.